<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /cvsroot/ignition/ignitionserver/docs/ignitionserver-docs.xml,v 1.1 2005/07/04 19:39:01 ziggythehamster Exp $ -->
<book>
	<bookinfo>
		<legalnotice>
			<para>
				ignitionServer and its included documentation are released under the GNU
				General Public License, Version 2.0, or at your option, any later version.
				You may distribute ignitionServer or its documentation only under these
				terms and conditions.
			</para>
		</legalnotice>
		<authorgroup>
			<author>
				<firstname>Keith</firstname>
				<surname>Gable</surname>
			</author>
		</authorgroup>
		<copyright>
			<year>2005</year>
			<holder>Keith Gable</holder>
		</copyright>
	</bookinfo>
	<title>ignitionServer Documentation</title>
	<titleabbrev>ignitionServer</titleabbrev>
	
	<preface id="doc-help">
		<?dbhtml filename="doc-help.html" ?>
		<title>About This Documentation</title>
		<para>
			This documentation was generated using DocBook and is intended to make it
			easier for us to maintain the documentation. If you find some information
			that needs to be in here that isn't, please tell us by sending an e-mail to
			<email>ziggy <emphasis role="strong">at</emphasis> ignition-project <emphasis role="strong">dot</emphasis> com</email>.
		</para>
	</preface>
	<chapter id="readme">
		<?dbhtml filename="readme.html" ?>
		<title>Readme</title>
		<section id="licenseinfo">
			<title>License Info</title>
			<para>
				The software you have downloaded is open source and protected under the GNU General
				Public License. For more information, read LICENSE.TXT (you should have been 
				presented this when you installed).
			</para>
			<para>
				We encourage you to read this file before making any changes to the ignitionServer 
				source code.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="supportinfo">
			<?dbhtml filename="support.html" ?>
			<title>Support Info</title>
			<para>
				Support may be obtained on our forums, located at
				<ulink url="http://www.ignition-project.com/forum/">http://www.ignition-project.com/forum</ulink>.
				Please make sure you ask in <emphasis>ignitionServer Support</emphasis>
				and not another forum.
			</para>
			<para>
				Also, as a general rule, please make sure you follow these policies before asking
				questions: 
				<ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html">http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html</ulink>
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="installation">
			<?dbhtml filename="installation.html" ?>
			<title>Installation</title>
			<para>
				ignitionServer should have come bundled with an installer. This installer runs on
				Windows 95, 98, Me, NT, 2000, XP, and 2003, and all included utilities should work on
				both Windows NT (NT/2000/XP/2003) and Windows 9x (95/98/Me) with the latest patches
				and service packs applied (however, there are known issues with some configurations
				of Windows XP Service Pack 2 -- please see the related FAQ entries later in the
				documentation). <emphasis>Running ignitionServer on Windows 9x is strongly
				discouraged!</emphasis>
			</para>
			<para>
				ignitionServer may run under UNIX/Linux with Wine or CrossOver Office, but we have
				not been successful in making it run (then again, we tried with ttydrv -- it might
				work with x11drv and the proper DLLs). If you need ignitionServer to run on this
				platform, you can either wait for ignitionServer NG, or you can see if you can get
				CodeWeavers (makers of CrossOver Office) to include support for ignitionServer in
				CrossOver (they charge for special requests like this, but generally speaking, they
				can make almost everything work). We can try to help you if you attempt to make
				ignitionServer run on UNIX/Linux, but our support will be very limited; we have
				other issues to attend to.
			</para>
			<para>
				<emphasis role="strong">After installing ignitionServer, you will need to configure
				it.</emphasis> To do this, browse to where you installed ignitionServer and open 
				<filename>ircx.conf</filename> in Notepad. <filename>ircx.conf</filename> is very
				well documented using comments (lines beginning with
				<computeroutput>#</computeroutput> -- <emphasis>these are IGNORED!</emphasis>).
				Please take the time to read all of the comments in this file, and you will
				know what to fill in the normal lines.
			</para>
			<para>
				You will most likely also want to edit your MOTD (Message of the Day). This file
				has no special format and is named <filename>ircx.motd</filename> in the same
				directory as <filename>ircx.conf</filename>. Keep in mind that some IRC clients
				are limited to 80 characters per line, and adding more will either trim the line
				or make it wrap to the next line. Do not include the standard "-" that appears at
				the beginning of the MOTD, the server adds this automatically to ensure full
				compatibility with IRC clients that expect MOTD content to begin with a "-".
			</para>
			<note>
				<title>X:DIE</title>
				<para>
					By default, the server has the special X:DIE line set to true (1). This
					WILL keep the server from starting, and it will make it throw errors like
					"Server Misconfigured". <emphasis>This is not a bug, it's fully
					intended!</emphasis> The reason we added this feature was to make sure that
					every ignitionServer user configures their server, and at the very least,
					changes the default passwords from "admin" to something else. Please make
					fully certain that you change the passwords before you start the server.
				</para>
				<para>
					To turn the "Server Misconfigured" message off, simply set X:DIE to false
					(0). If the server was already running when you changed this value, you
					may need to restart it. Under most cases, the "Restart" button in the
					ignitionServer Monitor should work, but if it does not, press Ctrl-Alt-Del
					on your keyboard and end the process named "ignitionServer.exe". Some
					versions of Windows may show a shortened version of this (in particular,
					Windows 2000 sometimes truncates it to "ignitionServer.").
				</para>
			</note>
		</section>
		<section id="faq">
			<?dbhtml filename="faq.html" ?>
			<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
			<note>
				<title>About This FAQ</title>
				<para>
					Older versions of ignitionServer (i.e. those that supported the MSN Chat
					control) were a bit easier to use/modify than this version. This version
					is actually a lot better than the old MSN-supporting version, has way less
					bugs, and is several thousand times faster.
				</para>
				<para>
					While we do not mind very much answering common questions in the support
					forums, we ask that you <emphasis>please</emphasis> read this FAQ before you
					ask questions on the forums. Most of the common questions are answered here.
				</para>
			</note>
			<qandaset defaultlabel="quanda">
				<qandaentry id="ignitionserver-no-ui">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>When I start ignitionServer, nothing comes
						up!</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							It's supposed to do this! ignitionServer now runs as a
							full-fledged daemon (Windows calls this a "background
							service"). You will not get any interface at all when
							you start ignitionServer (unless you're using the ignitionServer
							Monitor, which allows you to do a few things to the server, but
							it's not actually the server). If you are not sure you started
							it properly, start your IRC client and type:
						</para>
						<para>
							<userinput>/server localhost</userinput>
						</para>
						<para>
							If you connect to something, the server is running. A less
							time-intensive method would be to hit Ctrl-Alt-Del and see if
							the ignitionServer process is running.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="ignitionserver-wont-start">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>Why doesn't ignitionServer start?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							First, make sure you read the above question. Then, check the 
							following things:
							<orderedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>Is <filename>ircx.conf</filename> in the 
									same folder as ignitionServer?</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>Was <filename>ircx.conf</filename>
									configured properly? Make sure all of the
									parameters are set right and that you're
									not using P: lines that bind to an adapter
									that doesn't exist or to a port in use.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</orderedlist>
						</para>
						<para>
							If you diagnosed those things and still have a problem, make
							sure ignitionServer isn't already running. ignitionServer
							cannot, by default, be run more than one time. This is to
							prevent one copy of ignitionServer from spinning out of control
							by not being able to bind to the same ports/adapters as the
							currently running version. If you need to be able to run
							multiple copies of ignitionServer, see the "How do I run
							more than one copy of ignitionServer?" question below.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="ignitionserver-x-die">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>Why does ignitionServer send out Closing Link:
						(AutoKilled: Server Misconfigured [see ircx.conf]) and disconnect users
						on connection?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							In an earlier version of ignitionServer, we introduced a
							configuration option called X:DIE that is set to "1" (true)
							by default in all official distributions of ignitionServer.
							When this is set to true (1), the server will not allow anyone
							to connect to your server. <emphasis>This is to require that
							all server administrators read the configuration file and
							understand all of the data that has been entered in it.
							</emphasis> Before you can use ignitionServer, you
							<emphasis role="strong">must</emphasis> edit the configuration.
							In the process of configuring your server, you will notice
							X:DIE. Set this to 0 (false) to disable the "Server 
							Misconfigured" message.
						</para>
						<para>
							You may need to restart the server. The ignitionServer
							Monitor should work, but in the event it doesn't, you can try
							to end ignitionServer's process in the task manager (press
							Ctrl-Alt-Delete).
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="ignitionserver-suggested-os">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>What is the reccommended operating system for
						using ignitionServer?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							We reccommend using an operating system based on Windows NT,
							such as Windows 2000, Windows XP, or Windows Server 2003. For
							best performance, we suggest running on a server flavor of
							Windows, such as Windows 2000 Server, or Windows Server 2003.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="ignitionserver-violate-eula">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>Does ignitionServer violate my 
						<acronym>EULA</acronym>?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							Probably. We can't answer this for you though. You need to read 
							the End User License Agreement that came with your operating
							system. Most versions of Windows and Windows NT only allow 10 
							simultaneous connections in the EULA. ignitionServer, by design, 
							opens ports and connections as it needs to. At any one time,
							ignitionServer can have anywhere from 0 to 65535 connections 
							open. You take full legal responsibility if you decide to
							violate your EULA.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="ignitionserver-i-cant-connect">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>Why can't I connect to my ignitionServer
						installation?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							Are you connecting to the right address? Usually, you'll want to
							connect to "localhost" or "127.0.0.1". In mIRC, you'd go
							<userinput>/server localhost</userinput>. Other people
							will want to connect to your outgoing hostname or outgoing IP
							address. See the next question for more help on getting users to
							connect to your outbound address. If you are trying to connect
							to <systemitem class="domainname">localhost</systemitem> or 
							<systemitem class="ipaddress">127.0.0.1</systemitem>, make sure 
							ignitionServer is running and that it's running on port 6667 (or try
							<userinput>/server localhost <token>port</token></userinput>, 
							replacing <token>port</token> with
							whatever port you configured ignitionServer to run on.
						</para>
						<para>
							Also, newer versions of Windows, such as Windows XP Service Pack 
							2 and Windows Server 2003 require you specify a physical adapter
							instead of the loopback device (localhost). On these versions
							of Windows, you will have to change the M: line to specify
							an adapter to bind to, and you must connect to that address
							instead of localhost or 127.0.0.1. The proper address varies
							from system to system. You can get the address from the 
							<guilabel>Support</guilabel> tab of your default Internet
							connection's "Properties" window. You can view a list of all
							of your connections in "Network Connections" in the Control
							Panel. Usually, it's called "Local Area Connection".
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="igntiionserver-others-cant-connect">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>I can connect to my ignitionServer installation,
						but nobody else can, how can I fix this?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							First and foremost, are you giving your users the right
							address? Any IP address beginning with <systemitem class="ipaddress">172.16</systemitem>,
							<systemitem class="ipaddress">127</systemitem>, <systemitem
							class="ipaddress">192.168</systemitem> , or <systemitem class="ipaddress">10</systemitem>
							is called a "non-routable IP" -- i.e. it can only be used on
							your local network and not on the Internet. You must give your
							users your public IP address -- the one that every other
							computer on the Internet sees. To get your IP, go to a site like
							<ulink url="http://www.showmemyip.com/">http://www.showmemyip.com/</ulink>. <emphasis
							role="strong">By giving people your IP address, you are not particularly making
							yourself vulnerable in any way.</emphasis> The media has scared
							most people into thinking an IP address is some magic cookie that
							when found lets anyone hack into your computer. This is simply
							not true, and if someone tells you to go get a Dynamic DNS
							service to "mask" your IP, they don't know what they're
							talking about, because DNS is just a way to assign a name to
							an IP address -- the address is still readily available to
							anyone. In short, do not be afraid to hand out your IP address,
							just as long as you keep your computer up to date (because
							there are unfixed vulnerabilities in services that run by default
							on Windows, and if someone has your address and knows how to
							exploit these, some damage can be done -- but if your computer is
							kept up to date, you can't really get hacked).
						</para>
						<para>
							Here are other things to consider:
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>Is your router or firewall allowing port 
									6667 through to your machine? If it isn't, you
									need to make sure your firewall is properly 
									configured and that your router is forwarding
									port 6667 to your machine (see the manual - 
									usually it's something like "port forwarding",
									"virtual server", "network applications", etc.).
									</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>Are you behind a proxy? If you are behind 
									a proxy, you probably can't run ignitionServer 
									on the Internet.</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>It may help your users remember the
									address if you have a dynamic DNS service, which
									you can get at No-IP.com or DynDNS.org.</para>
								</listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="msn-wont-connect">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>Why doesn't MSN connect?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							A: ignitionServer does not support the MSN Chat Control. We will never add support for 
							this unless Microsoft decides to open their protocol and make it a standard, and even then
							it's not really likely we will add support for it. With the current state of licensing for
							MSN property, it is ILLEGAL to use the MSN Chat Control unless you are using it to connect
							to MSN) without official written permission from Microsoft Corporation, and even then,
							you had better make sure you have a good lawyer, because while they may license you to use
							the control, there is almost no chance they'll license their protocol and server
							implementation to you. In a nutshell, if you are wanting a server that supports the MSN
							Chat Control, you will probably be committing a crime by using it. I am not a lawyer, so
							you will probably want to talk to someone that is, if you really want to do the lame thing
							and use the MSN Chat Control to connect to a server. And please, save our support techs
							time and don't ask us this question!
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="alternatives-to-msn-webchat">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>Since you don't support the MSN Chat Control, what other solutions do you
							have for a good webchat?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							There are many good webchat clients. We are working on ignitionLite, which will work on
							Linux, Windows, MacOS X, FreeBSD, and any other platform supported by Firefox, Mozilla,
							Netscape, Safari, or Internet Explorer. Opera 8 and Konqueror may also work. This will be
							your best solution for a web chat client. We currently do not have a due date for
							ignitionLite, but we are trying to push some real code out before 2006. Then again, it's
							just a bunch of guys doing this in our spare time -- just be patient and when it's ready,
							we'll release it. You can get more information at
							<ulink url="http://www.ignition-project.com/ignition/lite/">http://www.ignition-project.com/ignition/lite/</ulink>.
						</para>
						<para>
							Since you probably need something <emphasis>now</emphasis>, we reccommend PJIRC, which is
							a fairly decent Java IRC client that is highly customizable and open source. You can get
							PJIRC from <ulink url="http://www.pjirc.com/">http://www.pjirc.com/</ulink>.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="is-ignitionserver-free">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>Is ignitionServer free?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							Absolutely. ignitionServer is avaliable under the GNU General Public License and is
							avaliable for download for free from SourceForge.net and our own website. The GPL,
							however, permits people to sell copies of any GPL software so long as the sourcecode
							is provided, for an equal or lesser amount than the compiled executable (binary). We
							cannot help you get your money back, because it's legal. However, if you bought
							ignitionServer, and feel you have been ripped off, see if the seller will give you a
							refund. Legitimate companies usually have a return policy. Just because you paid for a 
							copy of ignitionServer doesn't mean you were ripped off -- it's possible someone sold you
							a version with extra features or something -- which is fine, UNLESS they did not offer
							you sourcecode; and if they did this, PLEASE report this person to
							<email>gpl-violations <emphasis role="strong">at</emphasis> ignition-project <emphasis role="strong">dot</emphasis> com</email>
							immediately so we can seek legal action
							against	the person who sold our software to you.
						</para>
						<para>
							ignitionServer is also "free as in speech". That is, you're free to make whatever changes
							you want to our sourcecode (so long as you follow our licensing). For more information,
							please read <filename>license.txt</filename> in the docs directory.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="add-irc-operators">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>How do I add IRC operators?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							Open <filename>ircx.conf</filename> in <application>Notepad</application> and read it.
							About halfway down, there is a section for "IRC Operators". Read that section, it's fairly
							complete and has complete help for how to add IRC operators.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="highprot-and-lowprot">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>What is the difference between oper flag P and p?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							There are two differences:
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>Opers with +P cannot be kicked by opers with +p, even if you set
									+p to be a higher level in the channel than +P.</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>You can give +P different onjoin modes than +p, effectively giving
									an oper with HighProt (+P) higher privileges (or lower, if you want) than
									an oper with LowProt (+p).</para>
								</listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="where-are-services">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>Where are ChanServ/NickServ/MemoServ?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							Other IRCX servers (most notably <application>IRCXpro</application>) include the services
							inside the server. This is a bad, bandwidth-wasting idea. It requires that every server
							exchange the data about the users, rather than it being kept in a centralized place. It's
							also fairly difficult to make sure the data is regulated and only directly accessible 
							by a certain group of administrators. ignitionServer, however, handles services like every
							other self-respecting IRC server does. You connect services as a link (or, as the case
							will eventually be, as a service), and services does the job it needs to do. You need an
							IRC services that is compatible with standard RFC 1459 IRC (Anope works really good, I
							hear, but you'll need to compile your own; the only versions of Anope I see floating
							around only support UnrealIRCd.. also, I've never tested it myself, so it might not even
							work at all). You may also need to tweak some IRC server specific settings (i.e. you
							probably don't want to use Unreal's SVSMODE). If you want services specifically designed
							for Windows and ignitionServer, use ignitionServices. More information can be found at our
							website.
						</para>
						<para>
							P.S. We know that ignitionServices is fairly unmaintained. Please keep in mind the current
							release of ignitionServices should be considered "Alpha", and as such, expect it to do
							anything, ranging from not working at all to catching your computer on fire. It probably
							won't do either of those things, but there's a chance it will. In any event, we plan on
							writing a module for Anope to support ignitionServer, so we really have no intentions of
							making the current ignitionServices suck less. But, if we find something particularly
							nasty, we'll fix it.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="differences-between-irc-and-ircx">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>What's the difference between IRCD and IRCX?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							Simply put, nothing. There's a common misconception about these acronyms. An IRCX server
							is just as much an IRCD as any other type of IRC server. If you think that an IRCD means
							"a server that isn't IRCX", I probably just confused you. IRCD means "IRC server" (daemon
							is a word used by UNIX and UNIX-like systems [Linux] to mean "server", and the D in IRCD
							actually stands for daemon). IRCX means "Internet Relay Chat eXtensions". When IRCX is
							properly implemented, it is RFC 1459 (the IRC specification) plus the IRCX specification.
							IRCX is not a protocol, but an extension to a protocol. In theory, any regular RFC
							1459-compliant server can add these extensions. Many people think that IRCDs have weird
							modes and are "servers that are not IRCX". However, you could easily turn something like
							UnrealIRCD into an IRCX server, because IRCX only defines additions to the IRC protocol.
							In most circumstances, the differences between regular IRC, and IRC with the extensions
							(IRCX) are as follows:
						</para>
						<para>
							First off, IRCX adds several security-oriented commands, like ACCESS (get/set/unset who
							has access to what levels in a channel) and AUTH (show proof you have credentials to
							access the server). IRCX also adds another level of channel users, the owner. In RFC 1459,
							only hosts (@) and voices (+) were defined. Since RFC 1459's conception in the 80's, IRC
							servers have added many extra levels, so this is somewhat irrelevant. However, in true
							IRCX (which is RFC 1459 + extensions), there are only 3 levels: Owner (.), Host (@), and
							Voice (+). That doesn't include normal user, which has no prefix. You could, in theory,
							have more levels than this, but you may break some clients that don't properly support
							IRCX. IRCX also provides a mechanism for sending a message to a person WITHIN a channel.
							Before IRCX, any message you sent to a user was sent to them directly, out of any context
							of a channel. In IRCX, you can use the WHISPER command, and the message will only apply to
							that user within that channel. If they aren't in the channel, the message won't send, even
							if they're connected.
						</para>
						<para>
							IRCX also has channel metadata, or "properties", which set various channel settings, like
							the language spoken in the channel, the password required to be an owner, etc. Standard
							RFC 1459 IRC only has one key, and it's the key for getting into a locked room. The IRCX
							specification also calls for DATA/REQUEST/REPLY, which are very powerful commands. They
							are hardly used, but their applications are nearly limitless. You could use these commands
							for games, telling a special client to change the avatar displayed, and more. Microsoft 
							Comic Chat uses these commands for displaying expressions of the comic characters, telling
							other users what character you're using, and a lot more. IRC is more flat, and is designed
							for text-based communication. IRCX allows a bit more dynamic conversation, and that's why
							some people prefer it. However, some people like IRC better because oftentimes IRC servers
							are a lot more powerful and have more modes and features. IRCX also offers the ability to
							search for channels by certain properties, so a user could locate a channel that speaks
							their native language.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="reload-motd">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>How do I reload a modified MOTD?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							 As an operator (with rehash privledges), type <userinput>/rehash -MOTD</userinput>. This
							 will reload the Message of the Day.
						 </para>
					 </answer>
				 </qandaentry>
				 <qandaentry id="edit-motd">
					 <question>
						 <label>Q:</label> <para>How do I edit the Message of the Day?</para>
					 </question>
					 <answer>
						 <label>A:</label>
						 <para>
							 In the same folder as ignitionServer, there is a file called
							 <filename>ircx.motd</filename>. Open this file with Notepad and save it. If the server is
							 currently running, you will need to type <userinput>/rehash -MOTD</userinput> (see
							 above).
						 </para>
					 </answer>
				 </qandaentry>
				 <qandaentry id="auto-vhost">
					 <question>
						 <label>Q:</label> <para>How does the Auto VHost (X:AUTOVHOST) system work?</para>
					 </question>
					 <answer>
						 <label>A:</label>
						 <para>
							 The Auto VHost system is very simple to use and set up. Basically, it changes the
							 hostname of IRC operators to a specific Virtual Host (VHost) when they log in. For this
							 to work, there has to be an O: line and a V: line, both with the same credentials
							 (password/username/hostmask). The X:AUTOVHOST line also needs to be set to "1" (enabled).
							 Once these things are completed, operators can log in (with /oper), and they'll
							 automatically get their VHost if they have one. If an operator doesn't have a VHost, it
							 will be the same as if X:AUTOVHOST is off (0).
						 </para>
					 </answer>
				 </qandaentry>
				 <qandaentry id="error-writing-ignitionserver-exe">
					 <question>
						 <label>Q:</label> <para>How come I'm getting this error in the installer: Error Opening File for
							 Writing: "C:\Program Files\ignitionServer\ignitionServer.exe"?</para>
					 </question>
					 <answer>
						 <label>A:</label>
						 <para>
							You are attempting to update or uninstall ignitionServer while ignitionServer is running
							This cannot be done. To exit ignitionServer, hit Ctrl-Alt-Del, and stop the
							ignitionServer.exe process (or the task, on Win9x).
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="error-writing-monitor-exe">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>How come I'm getting this error in the installer: Error Opening File for
							Writing: "C:\Program Files\ignitionServer\monitor.exe"?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							You are attempting to update or uninstall ignitionServer while the monitor is running.
							This cannot be done. To exit the monitor, bring it up (from the system tray or taskbar),
							and press the close button in the corner.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="broken-l-lines">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>Why don't my L: lines work anymore?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							In ignitionServer 0.3.5, we reverted back to C: and N: lines for compatibility reasons.
							Please read <filename>ircx.conf</filename> for instructions on how to use C: and N: lines
							(they're nearly exactly the same). Sorry for any inconvenience.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry id="what-is-createmode">
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>What is X:CREATEMODE and how do I use it?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							X:CREATEMODE is a new X: line that we added to give server administrators greater control
							over their server. It allows the administrator to choose what group of users is able to
							create channels. In most cases, you will just want the default of 0, which allows all
							users to create channels. If you are setting up a premium chat service, or otherwise will
							only have a fixed set of channels, you will probably want to use 1, which will only allow
							IRC operators to create channels. In addition to this, you can force users to register and
							identify to NickServ before they can create channels. To do this, set X:CREATEMODE to 2.
							For more information, please read <filename>ircx.conf</filename> in your favorite text
							editor.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
				<qandaentry>
					<question>
						<label>Q:</label> <para>Why isn't ignitionServer working on Windows XP Service Pack 2 (and/or Windows Server 2003)?</para>
					</question>
					<answer>
						<label>A:</label>
						<para>
							Windows XP SP2 adds several security "enhancements", such as limiting the number of
							outbound connections, and introducing an artificial lag between the opening of outbound
							listening sockets. On a normal desktop system, these enhancements will probably prevent
							you from becoming a spam relay or zombie. When you're using your desktop system as a
							server by running ignitionServer, these enhancements become a serious bottleneck. It will
							also probably prevent ignitionServer from properly initializing (it will say "loaded OK"
							in the errorlog, becuase the Winsock subsystem is lying to ignitionServer).
						</para>
						<para>
							In order to make ignitionServer properly function on XP SP2, you must make changes to
							<filename>ircx.conf</filename> (since XP SP2 does not allow you to bind to all adapters as
							a security measure), and you may have to patch your TCP/IP subsystem to remove these
							security enhancements. <emphasis>Most of the previous also applies to Windows Server 2003,
							in particular, you will need to make some modifications to <filename>ircx.conf</filename>
							so that ignitionServer can work.</emphasis> <emphasis role="strong">WARNING: PATCHING
							TCPIP.SYS IS HIGHLY DISCOURAGED BY MICROSOFT AND IT MAY VOID YOUR WARRANTY. YOU ACCEPT ALL
							RISKS BY PATCHING YOUR TCP/IP SUBSYSTEM. BY PATCHING TCPIP.SYS, YOU AGREE NOT TO HOLD US
							LIABLE FOR ANY DAMAGES.</emphasis>
						</para>
						<para>
							You can get the instructions for patching TCPIP.SYS and modifying
							<filename>ircx.conf</filename> by clicking Start &gt; (All) Programs &gt; ignitionServer
							&gt; Documentation.
						</para>
					</answer>
				</qandaentry>
			</qandaset>
			<para>
				If you have any more questions, see our forum at <ulink
				url="http://www.ignition-project.com/forum/">http://www.ignition-project.com/forum/</ulink>.
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
</book>